and today we are going to talk about the
web GPU and how revolutionary it is for
the browsers developers and the web we
are also going to understand why web GPU
is a game changer for applications other
than video games a web GPU is a new
graphics API that is now available to
use in the latest update of Google
Chrome to understand why web GPU is a
big deal let's first understand what web
GPU was created to replace webgl there
was a time long long ago where browsers
were not as powerful as they are now but
then if you wanted to draw anything on
the screen of the user you would have to
use Flash which was a plugin not
included by the browser that we had to
install since the web was relying too
much on flash which was controlled by a
single company and since Steve Jobs did
not want to support Flash on the
iPhone's browser makers came up with a
solution to get a native graphics on the
web without using the third party plugin
this is when HD email 5 was released and
it came with a new HTML tag that was
groundbreaking back then and that was
the HTML5 canvas element the canvas
element has its name implies created a
canvas in which developers could draw
images on the user's screen at first it
only supported the drawing of two the
graphics it had limited features and it
was not so performant not good enough
for building a high performance game
then game webgl webgl was created to
bring 3d rendering to the web a webgl
was based on opengl an already existing
and known cross-platform API for two and
3D Graphics opengl is basically an
interface that developers can use to
talk to the GPU the graphic card of the
computer the thing is that opengl is
very old its initial release was in 1992
and it is not in active development
anymore this means it was created when
computers and gpus were not so powerful
and did things very different it also
means it won't get any new features and
because it has been around for such a
long time replacing it with something
completely new is easier than updating
it this is why the Chronos group an
organization behind opengl and webgl
stopped developing opengl and came up
with a Vulcan a completely new and
redesigned Graphics API Apple also came
up with metal their own Graphics API and
deprecated opengl on Mac OS and IO in
Microsoft came up with DirectX 12 for
Xbox and PC so this means that we ended
up with Vulcan metal and direct X12 all
new modern faster redesigned apis for
computer Graphics but the browser will
still stock using webgl enter web GPU
web GPU is a new browser API and it
allows websites to talk to chronos's
Vulcan Microsoft direct 3D and Apple's
metal web GPU is just a set of new
command that the browser understands the
browser for now Chrome and soon Firefox
and Safari will take those web GPU
commands and talk to the GPU using the
apis of the machine where the browser is
installed so if you use Chrome on a
Linux machine Chrome will use Vulcan if
you use it on a Windows machine Chrome
will use direct 3D which is the 3D part
of DirectX and if you use it on Apple
Chrome will use metal directly this is a
very big deal this means that websites
will now be able to use and have more
control over the GPU of the user as you
can imagine this unlocks a new platform
for gaming it was possible before to run
3D games on the web when there were
performance limitations if the browser
can now use the GPU fully then running
again from the browser instead of
downloading and installing it is going
to be an obvious choice desktop software
that uses the GPU like video and photo
editing programs could become truly a
hundred percent web based which is good
for my user's point of view and the
Publishers as well but apart from that
web GPU can be huge for AI as you know
gpus are heavily used on the training
and running of machine learning models
this is due to the fact that gpus are
good at doing parallel computation using
web GPU we can access the gpu's ability
to perform computations from the browser
which was not possible using webgl this
means that users could run machine
learning models from the browser itself
without any of their private data being
uploaded anywhere and never leaving
their device that will be so sweet it
will be cheaper for companies to run
their AI models since they can use the
processing power of the user's device it
would be more private since the data
never leaves the device and the AI could
potentially run offline web GPU support
for all sorts of things is starting to
increase machine learning libraries like
tensorflow.js already have a web GPU
backend 3D engines like Babylon JS and
3js have started supporting web GPU as
well even Unity the game engine is said
to be working on exporting to web GPU I
suspect this is how most of us will use
web GPU indirectly raw web GPU code is
verbose and long if you're curious this
is some of the code required to render a
triangle like this one on screen so I
think that what most of us will do is
use a library like 3js babylon.js or
tensorflow.js that supports web GPU keep
in mind that web GPU is not limited to
JavaScript only you can also use
languages like rust with libraries like
wgpu to write web GPU code and you can
run that code on the browser of the user
by compiling it to webassembly as always
with new technology comes new risk
nothing is a hundred percent good there
are always the downsides what makes web
GPU awesome is also what makes it
dangerous websites can now talk to your
GPU which means that in theory a website
could use this new feature and use your
GPU to mine a cryptocurrency every time
you visit it draining your resources and
battery life or it could potentially be
used for the anonymizing and tracking
users across the web we will have to
wait and see how browsers Implement web
GPU maybe the user will first have to
give permission just like with
geolocation which I think would be a
good thing to do now I want to know what
you think did you know about web GPU
what do you imagine is going to happen
do you feel comfortable allowing
websites to talk to your GPU let me know
in the comments I'm going to be looking
at them right now if you found this
video useful please consider liking it
and subscribing to the channel and don't
forget that if you want to learn things
like JavaScript python react react
native go Dart flutter among many many
others for absolutely free all you have
to do is click the link below to join
any of our many free courses that you
can take right now for absolutely free
with me click the link below and I will
see you there
see you on the next one bye
[Music]